My dream is to be a scientist,
but I enjoy games too much. What can I do?
Hello
I'm... What was I
going to say...
(audience laughter)
What grade are you in?
4th grade.
(Sunim) 4th grade?
Yes.
(Sunim) What worry do you have?
My dream is to become a scientist
that makes weapons.
But I like to play games.
(Sunim) Games?
Yes.
Scientists should like to do
science experiments.
But I like playing games.
What should I do?
(Audience Laughter)
(Sunim) Well I guess you can't
become a scientist then.
Huh?
But I want to be a scientist.
Then you should play less games.
Or you shouldn't play at all.
(Questioner) But I like games...
(Audience Laughter)
Then take a coin,
Write 'game' on one side and
'scientist' on the other side.
Flip the coin and
take the path it leads you.
You can't have both.
You can only choose one.
Which path will you choose?
(Sunim) Do you want to play games
or become a scientist?
I like both...
Doing both is difficult.
A long time ago, there was
a person quite like yourself.
He was asked whether
he wanted rice or alcohol
As compensation for his work.
He wanted both rice and alcohol.
What did he choose?
'Mix the rice with alcohol',
he said.
(Audience Laughter)
What you can do is,
You can play games really hard
and become a programmer.
It's a little different
from being a scientist.
A programmer that
makes games, you know?
Become a programmer.
You can do that.
To become a scientist,
you must do a lot of research.
Instead of playing
and having fun,
You need to study the
principle behind things
(Sunim) Rather than the
consequence.
(Sunim) Even if you like
both options,
What would you have to do now
If you're thinking of the future?
(Questioner) I should study.
You should study, right?
If you only stick to
things you like now,
it would be the same as
a mouse eating poison.
It tastes good now but
will cause a stomachache.
So now you must choose.
In India, I gathered kids and
Offered them to come to school,
but they wouldn't come.
So I gave them candy
when they'd come to school.
Kids would come,
but what for?
To get candy.
So after a month,
I'd ask them.
Do you want candy?
Or do you want to study?
By doing so, I'd separate them.
Younger kids would say
they want candy.
A couple of older ones
would want to study.
I'd move the ones who want to
study to a separate class.
I'd continue giving candy
to those who only want candy.
Although they like candy,
they'd hesitate.
They'd switch
back and forth
Between studying
and wanting candy.
If I ask 'Are you sure?',
they'd choose to study at first.
But if I say
'Don't you want candy?',
They'd go right back
to choosing candy.
If I ask, 'Don't you
need to study?',
They'd change their mind
and choose to study.
But in the long run,
what would they prefer?
(Questioner) Studying.
They'd want to study.
I understand that you
enjoy playing games.
But if your dream is to
become a scientist,
it will be difficult to become one
if you only play games.
It's fine to do so if you
want to run a small store,
(Sunum) Or become a farmer.
But to become a scientist,
you'd have to study hard.
You'd have to, don't you?
(Questioner) Yes.
You need to attend a university.
Can you attend university
without studying?
(Questioner) I can't.
(Sunim) No, you can't.
So you need to decide.
(Sunim) No matter how young you are,
you should take the responsibility.
Nothing is absolute,
But to become a scientist,
what must you focus on?
(Questioner) Studying
(Sunim) Let me tell you
about my story
(Sunim) When I was in
middle school,
(Sunim) I rented a room
and lived by myself.
I cooked for myself and
attended school by myself
Since I was in middle school.
Instead of using one
briquette a day, I'd be frugal.
I'd use 2 briquettes across 3 days
by closing the furnace door tightly.
I'd block it out.
I'm sure you don't know
what I'm talking about.
(Sunim) Anyway,
the room would be chilly.
But there's one spot on the floor
where the furnace is.
If you put a blanket over it,
it would get warm.
The rest of the room
would be icy cold.
It was so cold that the ink
at my desk would freeze.
If I study at my desk,
my body would freeze.
Winters were cold.
I'd be tempted to put my feet
underneath the blankets.
They'd be warm.
Then I'd start thinking,
'I'll just study laying down
for a while'.
'I'll move back
to my desk in a bit.'
And yet once I lay down,
I wouldn't last 10 minute
and fall asleep.
This repeated every night.
I'd start out at my desk
and feel cold.
I'd put my feet under the
blanket and fall asleep.
I'd start off sitting at my desk,
but soon be tempted.
There was no adult to
scold me since I lived alone.
So I put up a sign on the wall
in front of my desk.
Just like your dream of becoming
a scientist, I had a dream too.
I wrote : "My dream is
such and such."
"To accomplish my dream,
I won't put my feet under the blanket"
For you to
become a scientist,
You should avoid playing
games all the time.
(Questioner) I understand.
That's what you can do for now.
Will you try it?
(Questioner) I will.
Great.
(Audience Laughter, Applause)
With that kind of determination,
I think you'll make it.
Don't do think so?
Even if you end up
play games again tomorrow,
The fact that you made up your mind
here today will become a start.
Do you understand?
As you've planted the seed,
If your love for games
are at 100,
It will likely decrease
to about 80.
You'll start thinking of the fact
that you need to study.
Everyone has temptations
at that age.
You're tempted
to do fun things.
And yet if you
only have fun,
You can't accomplish
big things in life.
You need to overcome temptation
and take interest in other things.
There's a saying,
'Overcoming yourself is'
'Harder than overcoming
an army of a million'
You need to overcome yourself.
You need to practice overcoming
temptations from childhood.
If you surrender to your karma,
your temptations,
Playing games won't be
your last temptation.
There will be many other
temptations across your life.
You will likely surrender
to them every time.
Therefore you should
start practicing now.